<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Version Control and Git | Academic</title>
    <link>https://example.com/tag/version-control-and-git/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/tag/version-control-and-git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Version Control and Git</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Version Control and Git</title>
      <link>https://example.com/tag/version-control-and-git/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version control. Git.</title>
      <link>https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About Version Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is “version control”, and why should you care? Version control is a system that records changes to a file or set of files over time so that you can recall specific versions later. For the examples in this book, you will use software source code as the files being version controlled, though in reality you can do this with nearly any type of file on a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a graphic or web designer and want to keep every version of an image or layout (which you would most certainly want to), a Version Control System (VCS) is a very wise thing to use. It allows you to revert selected files back to a previous state, revert the entire project back to a previous state, compare changes over time, see who last modified something that might be causing a problem, who introduced an issue and when, and more. Using a VCS also generally means that if you screw things up or lose files, you can easily recover. In addition, you get all this for very little overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local Version Control Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people’s version-control method of choice is to copy files into another directory (perhaps a time-stamped directory, if they’re clever). This approach is very common because it is so simple, but it is also incredibly error prone. It is easy to forget which directory you’re in and accidentally write to the wrong file or copy over files you don’t mean to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To deal with this issue, programmers long ago developed local VCSs that had a simple database that kept all the changes to files under revision control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;local&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/version-control.-git./local_hufcb633eabb4ce248b64f5422c2c69f5a_20255_20822e8017c177cf18983f1a44f65d06.webp 400w,
               /post/version-control.-git./local_hufcb633eabb4ce248b64f5422c2c69f5a_20255_0de96a6d72e1228a7498fded8ce5b989.webp 760w,
               /post/version-control.-git./local_hufcb633eabb4ce248b64f5422c2c69f5a_20255_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./local_hufcb633eabb4ce248b64f5422c2c69f5a_20255_20822e8017c177cf18983f1a44f65d06.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;649&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Figure 1. Local version control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular VCS tools was a system called RCS, which is still distributed with many computers today. RCS works by keeping patch sets (that is, the differences between files) in a special format on disk; it can then re-create what any file looked like at any point in time by adding up all the patches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centralized Version Control Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next major issue that people encounter is that they need to collaborate with developers on other systems. To deal with this problem, Centralized Version Control Systems (CVCSs) were developed. These systems (such as CVS, Subversion, and Perforce) have a single server that contains all the versioned files, and a number of clients that check out files from that central place. For many years, this has been the standard for version control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;centralized&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/version-control.-git./centralized_hu74fb508a0af33a33fa0f541a94378552_22810_f93c80165d69b5e8aac99f5f188e2113.webp 400w,
               /post/version-control.-git./centralized_hu74fb508a0af33a33fa0f541a94378552_22810_b9d41468a9ebfde9114e38056a73f977.webp 760w,
               /post/version-control.-git./centralized_hu74fb508a0af33a33fa0f541a94378552_22810_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./centralized_hu74fb508a0af33a33fa0f541a94378552_22810_f93c80165d69b5e8aac99f5f188e2113.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;528&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Figure 2. Centralized version control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This setup offers many advantages, especially over local VCSs. For example, everyone knows to a certain degree what everyone else on the project is doing. Administrators have fine-grained control over who can do what, and it’s far easier to administer a CVCS than it is to deal with local databases on every client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this setup also has some serious downsides. The most obvious is the single point of failure that the centralized server represents. If that server goes down for an hour, then during that hour nobody can collaborate at all or save versioned changes to anything they’re working on. If the hard disk the central database is on becomes corrupted, and proper backups haven’t been kept, you lose absolutely everything — the entire history of the project except whatever single snapshots people happen to have on their local machines. Local VCSs suffer from this same problem — whenever you have the entire history of the project in a single place, you risk losing everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed Version Control Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where Distributed Version Control Systems (DVCSs) step in. In a DVCS (such as Git, Mercurial, Bazaar or Darcs), clients don’t just check out the latest snapshot of the files; rather, they fully mirror the repository, including its full history. Thus, if any server dies, and these systems were collaborating via that server, any of the client repositories can be copied back up to the server to restore it. Every clone is really a full backup of all the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;distributed&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/version-control.-git./distributed_hu7dff96406965f7bb87732a216019226c_26657_7cc702330d2d251a91f6efbc3ed41fb7.webp 400w,
               /post/version-control.-git./distributed_hu7dff96406965f7bb87732a216019226c_26657_c8b5ac17e6ced08e9f31c3db3ea44837.webp 760w,
               /post/version-control.-git./distributed_hu7dff96406965f7bb87732a216019226c_26657_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./distributed_hu7dff96406965f7bb87732a216019226c_26657_7cc702330d2d251a91f6efbc3ed41fb7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;635&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Figure 3. Distributed version control&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, many of these systems deal pretty well with having several remote repositories they can work with, so you can collaborate with different groups of people in different ways simultaneously within the same project. This allows you to set up several types of workflows that aren’t possible in centralized systems, such as hierarchical models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is Git?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is Git in a nutshell? This is an important section to absorb, because if you understand what Git is and the fundamentals of how it works, then using Git effectively will probably be much easier for you. As you learn Git, try to clear your mind of the things you may know about other VCSs, such as CVS, Subversion or Perforce — doing so will help you avoid subtle confusion when using the tool. Even though Git’s user interface is fairly similar to these other VCSs, Git stores and thinks about information in a very different way, and understanding these differences will help you avoid becoming confused while using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snapshots, Not Differences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major difference between Git and any other VCS (Subversion and friends included) is the way Git thinks about its data. Conceptually, most other systems store information as a list of file-based changes. These other systems (CVS, Subversion, Perforce, Bazaar, and so on) think of the information they store as a set of files and the changes made to each file over time (this is commonly described as delta-based version control).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 4. Storing data as changes to a base version of each file&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/version-control.-git./deltas_hu21e752c02fb2d6467a535fe251a4574d_16116_15b36e6504fa16379495b1abfe1803bb.webp 400w,
               /post/version-control.-git./deltas_hu21e752c02fb2d6467a535fe251a4574d_16116_6cfaac9b7817dde3057fe4bc5a5c6546.webp 760w,
               /post/version-control.-git./deltas_hu21e752c02fb2d6467a535fe251a4574d_16116_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./deltas_hu21e752c02fb2d6467a535fe251a4574d_16116_15b36e6504fa16379495b1abfe1803bb.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;295&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Figure 4. Storing data as changes to a base version of each file&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git doesn’t think of or store its data this way. Instead, Git thinks of its data more like a series of snapshots of a miniature filesystem. With Git, every time you commit, or save the state of your project, Git basically takes a picture of what all your files look like at that moment and stores a reference to that snapshot. To be efficient, if files have not changed, Git doesn’t store the file again, just a link to the previous identical file it has already stored. Git thinks about its data more like a &lt;strong&gt;stream of snapshots&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Figure 5. Storing data as snapshots of the project over time&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/version-control.-git./snapshots_hu92accb2b3854bd6a22d5da940afd496e_20722_33d347f182d951c65aafa5bf3c74caa6.webp 400w,
               /post/version-control.-git./snapshots_hu92accb2b3854bd6a22d5da940afd496e_20722_1b2605d871cd0c2471c5a81420c97467.webp 760w,
               /post/version-control.-git./snapshots_hu92accb2b3854bd6a22d5da940afd496e_20722_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/post/version-control.-git./snapshots_hu92accb2b3854bd6a22d5da940afd496e_20722_33d347f182d951c65aafa5bf3c74caa6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;290&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;em&gt;Figure 5. Storing data as snapshots of the project over time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important distinction between Git and nearly all other VCSs. It makes Git reconsider almost every aspect of version control that most other systems copied from the previous generation. This makes Git more like a mini filesystem with some incredibly powerful tools built on top of it, rather than simply a VCS. We’ll explore some of the benefits you gain by thinking of your data this way when we cover Git branching in Git Branching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nearly Every Operation Is Local&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most operations in Git need only local files and resources to operate — generally no information is needed from another computer on your network. If you’re used to a CVCS where most operations have that network latency overhead, this aspect of Git will make you think that the gods of speed have blessed Git with unworldly powers. Because you have the entire history of the project right there on your local disk, most operations seem almost instantaneous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, to browse the history of the project, Git doesn’t need to go out to the server to get the history and display it for you — it simply reads it directly from your local database. This means you see the project history almost instantly. If you want to see the changes introduced between the current version of a file and the file a month ago, Git can look up the file a month ago and do a local difference calculation, instead of having to either ask a remote server to do it or pull an older version of the file from the remote server to do it locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that there is very little you can’t do if you’re offline or off VPN. If you get on an airplane or a train and want to do a little work, you can commit happily (to your local copy, remember?) until you get to a network connection to upload. If you go home and can’t get your VPN client working properly, you can still work. In many other systems, doing so is either impossible or painful. In Perforce, for example, you can’t do much when you aren’t connected to the server; in Subversion and CVS, you can edit files, but you can’t commit changes to your database (because your database is offline). This may not seem like a huge deal, but you may be surprised what a big difference it can make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git Generally Only Adds Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do actions in Git, nearly all of them only add data to the Git database. It is hard to get the system to do anything that is not undoable or to make it erase data in any way. As with any VCS, you can lose or mess up changes you haven’t committed yet, but after you commit a snapshot into Git, it is very difficult to lose, especially if you regularly push your database to another repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes using Git a joy because we know we can experiment without the danger of severely screwing things up. For a more in-depth look at how Git stores its data and how you can recover data that seems lost, see Undoing Things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
